<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml><records><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Chen, Tianqi</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>A Review of Research on Social Network Event Detection Methods</title><secondary-title>International Journal of Computer Science and Information Technology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>International Journal of Computer Science and Information Technology</full-title><abbr-1>IJCSIT</abbr-1></periodical><pages>82-92</pages><volume>3</volume><number>1</number><issue>1</issue><dates><year>2024</year><pub-dates><date>2024-06-15</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>3005-7140, 3005-9682</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.62051/ijcsit.v3n1.12</electronic-resource-num><abstract>In recent years, with the development of technological infrastructure and the use of tech products, internet usage has become widespread globally. Significant advancements have been made in the use of social networks, which are now more readily accessible through Internet and Web 3.0 technologies such as Facebook, Twitter, and Instagram. Consequently, over the past decade, numerous researchers have been developing methods for event detection based on data collected from social media platforms. The methodologies devised for discovering events are typically modular in design and novel in terms of scale and speed. To review the research in this field, we have compiled existing works on social network event detection and conducted a comprehensive and indepth survey. Methods for social network event detection are elaborated and categorized, with performance evaluations conducted using relevant metrics. Finally, we offer perspectives on future directions.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://wepub.org/index.php/IJCSIT/article/view/1992</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\A4VQPSE6\Chen - 2024 - A Review of Research on Social Network Event Detection Methods.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-03-31 16:25:40</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Han, Zixuan</author><author>Shi, Leilei</author><author>Liu, Lu</author><author>Jiang, Liang</author><author>Fang, Jiawei</author><author>Lin, Fanyuan</author><author>Zhang, Jinjuan</author><author>Panneerselvam, John</author><author>Antonopoulos, Nick</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>A Survey on Event Tracking in Social Media Data Streams</title></titles><dates/><abstract>Social networks are inevitable parts of our daily life, where an unprecedented amount of complex data corresponding to a diverse range of applications are generated. As such, it is imperative to conduct research on social events and patterns from the perspectives of conventional sociology to optimize services that originate from social networks. Event tracking in social networks finds various applications, such as network security and societal governance, which involves analyzing data generated by user groups on social networks in real time. Moreover, as deep learning techniques continue to advance and make important breakthroughs in various fields, researchers are using this technology to progressively optimize the effectiveness of Event Detection (ED) and tracking algorithms. In this regard, this paper presents an in-depth comprehensive review of the concept and methods involved in ED and tracking in social networks. We introduce mainstream event tracking methods, which involve three primary technical steps: ED, event propagation, and event evolution. Finally, we introduce benchmark datasets and evaluation metrics for ED and tracking, which allow comparative analysis on the performance of mainstream methods. Finally, we present a comprehensive analysis of the main research findings and existing limitations in this field, as well as future research prospects and challenges.</abstract><remote-database-name>Zotero</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\S8VDRIMJ\Han et al. - A Survey on Event Tracking in Social Media Data Streams.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Conference Proceedings">10</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Qiu, Zitai</author><author>Ma, Congbo</author><author>Wu, Jia</author><author>Yang, Jian</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>An Efficient Automatic Meta-Path Selection for Social Event Detection via Hyperbolic Space</title><secondary-title>WWW '24: The ACM Web Conference 2024</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Proceedings of the ACM Web Conference 2024</full-title></periodical><pages>2519-2529</pages><dates><year>2024</year><pub-dates><date>2024-05-13</date></pub-dates></dates><publisher>ACM</publisher><isbn>979-8-4007-0171-9</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1145/3589334.3645526</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Social events reflect changes in communities, such as natural disasters and emergencies. Detection of these situations can help residents and organizations in the community avoid danger and reduce losses. The complex nature of social messages makes social event detection on social media challenging. The challenges that have a greater impact on social media detection models are as follows: (1) the amount of social media data is huge but its availability is small; (2) social media data is a tree structure and traditional Euclidean space embedding will distort embedded features; and (3) the heterogeneity of social media networks makes existing models unable to capture rich information well. To solve the above challenges, we propose a Heterogeneous Information Graph representation via Hyperbolic space combined with an Automatic Meta-path selection (GraphHAM) model, an efficient framework that automatically selects the meta-path’s weight and combines hyperbolic space to learn information on social media. In particular, we apply an efficient automatic meta-path selection technique and convert the selected meta-path into a vector, thereby reducing the requisite amount of labeled data for the model. We also design a novel Hyperbolic Multi-Layer Perceptron (HMLP) to further learn the semantic and structural information of social information. Extensive experiments show that GraphHAM can achieve outstanding performance on real-world data using only 20% of the whole dataset as the training set. Our code can be found on GitHub 1.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3589334.3645526</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\LAA8EVHU\Qiu et al. - 2024 - An Efficient Automatic Meta-Path Selection for Social Event Detection via Hyperbolic Space.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-03-31 16:26:39</access-date><custom1>Singapore Singapore</custom1><custom3>Proceedings of the ACM Web Conference 2024</custom3></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Conference Proceedings">10</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Ray, Marjolaine</author><author>Wang, Qi</author><author>Mélanie-Becquet, Frédérique</author><author>Poibeau, Thierry</author><author>Mazoyer, Béatrice</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>An Incremental Clustering Baseline for Event Detection on Twitter</title></titles><periodical><full-title>Proceedings of the Workshop on the Future of Event Detection (FuturED)</full-title></periodical><pages>18-24</pages><keywords><keyword>Computer Science - Computation and Language</keyword><keyword>Computer Science - Social and Information Networks</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2024</year><pub-dates><date>2024</date></pub-dates></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.18653/v1/2024.futured-1.2</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Event detection in text streams is a crucial task for the analysis of online media and social networks. One of the current challenges in this field is establishing a performance standard while maintaining an acceptable level of computational complexity. In our study, we use an incremental clustering algorithm combined with recent advancements in sentence embeddings. Our objective is to compare our findings with previous studies, specifically those by Cao et al. (2024) and Mazoyer et al. (2020). Our results demonstrate significant improvements and could serve as a relevant baseline for future research in this area.</abstract><remote-database-name>arXiv.org</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>http://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15257</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\5SI9BEPU\Ray et al. - 2024 - An Incremental Clustering Baseline for Event Detection on Twitter.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-03-31 16:26:49</access-date><custom3>Proceedings of the Workshop on the Future of Event Detection (FuturED)</custom3></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><contributors><authors><author>Yu, Xiaoyan</author><author>Wei, Yifan</author><author>Li, Pu</author><author>Zhou, Shuaishuai</author><author>Peng, Hao</author><author>Sun, Li</author><author>Zhu, Liehuang</author><author>Yu, Philip S.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>DAMe: Personalized Federated Social Event Detection with Dual Aggregation Mechanism</title><short-title>DAMe</short-title></titles><keywords><keyword>Computer Science - Computation and Language</keyword><keyword>Computer Science - Artificial Intelligence</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2024</year><pub-dates><date>2024-09-01</date></pub-dates></dates><publisher>arXiv</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.48550/arXiv.2409.00614</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Training social event detection models through federated learning (FedSED) aims to improve participants’ performance on the task. However, existing federated learning paradigms are inadequate for achieving FedSED’s objective and exhibit limitations in handling the inherent heterogeneity in social data. This paper proposes a personalized federated learning framework with a dual aggregation mechanism for social event detection, namely DAMe. We present a novel local aggregation strategy utilizing Bayesian optimization to incorporate global knowledge while retaining local characteristics. Moreover, we introduce a global aggregation strategy to provide clients with maximum external knowledge of their preferences. In addition, we incorporate a global-local event-centric constraint to prevent local overfitting and “client-drift”. Experiments within a realistic simulation of a natural federated setting, utilizing six social event datasets spanning six languages and two social media platforms, along with an ablation study, have demonstrated the effectiveness of the proposed framework. Further robustness analyses have shown that DAMe is resistant to injection attacks.</abstract><research-notes>Comment: CIKM 2024</research-notes><remote-database-name>arXiv.org</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.00614</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\NZDEM58F\Yu et al. - 2024 - DAMe Personalized Federated Social Event Detection with Dual Aggregation Mechanism.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-03-31 16:26:59</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><contributors><authors><author>Abagissa, Asres Temam</author><author>Saxena, Shruti</author><author>Chandra, Joydeep</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Distilbert-gnn: a Powerful Approach to Social Media Event Detection</title><short-title>Distilbert-gnn</short-title></titles><dates><year>2024</year><pub-dates><date>2024-04-04</date></pub-dates></dates><publisher>In Review</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.21203/rs.3.rs-4193412/v1</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Finding events actively discussed locally or globally is a signiﬁcant problem when mining social media data streams. Identifying such events can serve as an early warning system in an event such as an accident, a protest, an election, or other breaking news. However, with the massive volume of social media feeds streaming, early detection of such events is inherently complex. Despite the advances in social media event detection, existing methods often struggle with the dynamic nature of social media, the volume and velocity of data, and the ambiguity in usergenerated content. On the contrary, several relational aspects are present in social media that, if suitably handled and exploited, can improve detection performance. To mitigate these challenges, we propose ”DistilBERT-GNN,” an incremental event detection framework that leverages DistilBERT and Graph Neural Networks (GNNs). By integrating DistilBERT’s real-time contextual understanding with GNNs’ ability to capture evolving relationships in social media networks, our framework aims to detect and track events as they emerge and evolve. We assess the eﬀectiveness of our approach through comparative analysis against various state-of-the-art event detection methods on a real-world Twitter dataset. Our experimental result demonstrates that DistilBERT-GNN outperforms the baselines with NMI, AMI, and ARI metrics by 0.72, 0.53, and 0.24, respectively.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://www.researchsquare.com/article/rs-4193412/v1</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\RZUZNWCP\Abagissa et al. - 2024 - Distilbert-gnn a Powerful Approach to Social Media Event Detection.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-03-31 16:27:04</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Kovalchuk, Mikhail Andeevich</author><author>Filatova, Anastasiia</author><author>Korneev, Aleksei</author><author>Koreneva, Mariia</author><author>Nasonov, Denis</author><author>Voskresenskii, Aleksandr</author><author>Boukhanovsky, Alexander</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>SemConvTree: Semantic Convolutional Quadtrees for Multi-Scale Event Detection in Smart City</title><secondary-title>Smart Cities</secondary-title><short-title>SemConvTree</short-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Smart Cities</full-title><abbr-1>Smart Cities</abbr-1></periodical><pages>2763-2780</pages><volume>7</volume><number>5</number><issue>5</issue><dates><year>2024</year><pub-dates><date>2024-09-28</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>2624-6511</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.3390/smartcities7050107</electronic-resource-num><abstract>The digital world is increasingly permeating our reality, creating a significant reflection of the processes and activities occurring in smart cities. Such activities include well-known urban events, celebrations, and those with a very local character. These widespread events have a significant influence on shaping the spirit and atmosphere of urban environments. This work presents SemConvTree, an enhanced semantic version of the ConvTree algorithm. It incorporates the semantic component of data through semi-supervised learning of a topic modeling ensemble, which consists of improved models: BERTopic, TSB-ARTM, and SBert-Zero-Shot. We also present an improved event search algorithm based on both statistical evaluations and semantic analysis of posts. This algorithm allows for fine-tuning the mechanism of discovering the required entities with the specified particularity (such as a particular topic). Experimental studies were conducted within the area of New York City. They showed an improvement in the detection of posts devoted to events (about 40% higher f1-score) due to the accurate handling of events of different scales. These results suggest the long-term potential for creating a semantic platform for the analysis and monitoring of urban events in the future.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://www.mdpi.com/2624-6511/7/5/107</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\23L5L2DC\Kovalchuk et al. - 2024 - SemConvTree Semantic Convolutional Quadtrees for Multi-Scale Event Detection in Smart City.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-03-31 16:27:14</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><contributors><authors><author>Zhang, Kun</author><author>Yu, Xiaoyan</author><author>Li, Pu</author><author>Peng, Hao</author><author>Yu, Philip S.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>SocialED: A Python Library for Social Event Detection</title><short-title>SocialED</short-title></titles><keywords><keyword>Computer Science - Social and Information Networks</keyword><keyword>Computer Science - Digital Libraries</keyword><keyword>Computer Science - Machine Learning</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2024</year><pub-dates><date>2024-12-18</date></pub-dates></dates><publisher>arXiv</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.48550/arXiv.2412.13472</electronic-resource-num><abstract>SocialED is a comprehensive, open-source Python library designed to support social event detection (SED) tasks, integrating 19 detection algorithms and 14 diverse datasets. It provides a unified API with detailed documentation, offering researchers and practitioners a complete solution for event detection in social media. The library is designed with modularity in mind, allowing users to easily adapt and extend components for various use cases. SocialED supports a wide range of preprocessing techniques, such as graph construction and tokenization, and includes standardized interfaces for training models and making predictions. By integrating popular deep learning frameworks, SocialED ensures high efficiency and scalability across both CPU and GPU environments. The library is built adhering to high code quality standards, including unit testing, continuous integration, and code coverage, ensuring that SocialED delivers robust, maintainable software. SocialED is publicly available at https://github.com/RingBDStack/SocialED and can be installed via PyPI.</abstract><research-notes>Comment: 8 pages, 1 figure, Python library</research-notes><remote-database-name>arXiv.org</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>http://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13472</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\KJWF2DPD\Zhang et al. - 2024 - SocialED A Python Library for Social Event Detection.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-03-31 16:27:18</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><contributors><authors><author>Yu, Xiaoyan</author><author>Wei, Yifan</author><author>Zhou, Shuaishuai</author><author>Yang, Zhiwei</author><author>Sun, Li</author><author>Peng, Hao</author><author>Zhu, Liehuang</author><author>Yu, Philip S.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Towards Effective, Efficient and Unsupervised Social Event Detection in the Hyperbolic Space</title></titles><keywords><keyword>Computer Science - Computation and Language</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2024</year><pub-dates><date>2024-12-14</date></pub-dates></dates><publisher>arXiv</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.48550/arXiv.2412.10712</electronic-resource-num><abstract>The vast, complex, and dynamic nature of social message data has posed challenges to social event detection (SED). Despite considerable effort, these challenges persist, often resulting in inadequately expressive message representations (ineffective) and prolonged learning durations (inefficient). In response to the challenges, this work introduces an unsupervised framework, HyperSED (Hyperbolic SED). Specifically, the proposed framework first models social messages into semantic-based message anchors, and then leverages the structure of the anchor graph and the expressiveness of the hyperbolic space to acquire structure- and geometry-aware anchor representations. Finally, HyperSED builds the partitioning tree of the anchor message graph by incorporating differentiable structural information as the reflection of the detected events. Extensive experiments on public datasets demonstrate HyperSED’s competitive performance, along with a substantial improvement in efficiency compared to the current state-of-the-art unsupervised paradigm. Statistically, HyperSED boosts incremental SED by an average of 2%, 2%, and 25% in NMI, AMI, and ARI, respectively; enhancing efficiency by up to 37.41 times and at least 12.10 times, illustrating the advancement of the proposed framework. Our code is publicly available at https://github.com/ XiaoyanWork/HyperSED.</abstract><research-notes>Comment: Accepted to AAAI 2025</research-notes><remote-database-name>arXiv.org</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>http://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10712</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\VW47P7LD\Yu et al. - 2024 - Towards Effective, Efficient and Unsupervised Social Event Detection in the Hyperbolic Space.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-03-31 16:27:26</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Murthy, Dhiraj</author><author>Kurz, Sophia Elisavet</author><author>Anand, Tanvi</author><author>Hornick, Sonali</author><author>Lakuduva, Nandhini</author><author>Sun, Jerry</author></authors><secondary-authors><author>Nola, Iskra Alexandra</author></secondary-authors></contributors><titles><title>Examining hurricane–related social media topics longitudinally and at scale: A transformer-based approach</title><secondary-title>PLOS ONE</secondary-title><short-title>Examining hurricane–related social media topics longitudinally and at scale</short-title></titles><periodical><full-title>PLOS ONE</full-title><abbr-1>PLoS ONE</abbr-1></periodical><pages>e0316852</pages><volume>20</volume><number>1</number><issue>1</issue><dates><year>2025</year><pub-dates><date>2025-1-24</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>1932-6203</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1371/journal.pone.0316852</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Instead of turning to emergency phone systems, social media platforms, such as Twitter, have emerged as alternative and sometimes preferred venues for members of the public in the US to communicate during hurricanes and other natural disasters. However, relevant posts are likely to be missed by responders given the volume of content on platforms. Previous work successfully identified relevant posts through machine-learned methods, but depended on human annotators. Our study indicates that a GPU-accelerated version of BERTopic, a transformer-based topic model, can be used without human training to successfully discern topics during multiple hurricanes. We use 1.7 million tweets from four US hurricanes over seven years and categorize identified topics as temporal constructs. Some of the more prominent topics related to disaster relief, user concerns, and weather conditions. Disaster managers can use our model, data, and constructs to be aware of the types of themes social media users are producing and consuming during hurricanes.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://dx.plos.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0316852</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\D6ESG4LE\Murthy et al. - 2025 - Examining hurricane–related social media topics longitudinally and at scale A transformer-based app.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-03-31 16:27:32</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Conference Proceedings">10</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Yue, Zhenrui</author><author>Zeng, Huimin</author><author>Lan, Mengfei</author><author>Ji, Heng</author><author>Wang, Dong</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Zero- and Few-Shot Event Detection via Prompt-Based Meta Learning</title><secondary-title>Proceedings of the 61st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 1: Long Papers)</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Proceedings of the 61st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 1: Long Papers)</full-title></periodical><pages>7928-7943</pages><dates><year>2023</year><pub-dates><date>2023</date></pub-dates></dates><publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.18653/v1/2023.acl-long.440</electronic-resource-num><abstract>With emerging online topics as a source for numerous new events, detecting unseen / rare event types presents an elusive challenge for existing event detection methods, where only limited data access is provided for training. To address the data scarcity problem in event detection, we propose MetaEvent, a meta learningbased framework for zero- and few-shot event detection. Specifically, we sample training tasks from existing event types and perform meta training to search for optimal parameters that quickly adapt to unseen tasks. In our framework, we propose to use the clozebased prompt and a trigger-aware soft verbalizer to efficiently project output to unseen event types. Moreover, we design a contrastive meta objective based on maximum mean discrepancy (MMD) to learn class-separating features. As such, the proposed MetaEvent can perform zero-shot event detection by mapping features to event types without any prior knowledge. In our experiments, we demonstrate the effectiveness of MetaEvent in both zero-shot and few-shot scenarios, where the proposed method achieves state-of-the-art performance in extensive experiments on benchmark datasets FewEvent and MAVEN.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://aclanthology.org/2023.acl-long.440</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\HTC5QNHF\Yue et al. - 2023 - Zero- and Few-Shot Event Detection via Prompt-Based Meta Learning.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-03-31 16:49:10</access-date><custom1>Toronto, Canada</custom1><custom3>Proceedings of the 61st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 1: Long Papers)</custom3></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Kolajo, Taiwo</author><author>Daramola, Olawande</author><author>Adebiyi, Ayodele A.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Real-time event detection in social media streams through semantic analysis of noisy terms</title><secondary-title>Journal of Big Data</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Big Data</full-title><abbr-1>J Big Data</abbr-1></periodical><pages>90</pages><volume>9</volume><number>1</number><issue>1</issue><dates><year>2022</year><pub-dates><date>12/2022</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>2196-1115</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1186/s40537-022-00642-y</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Interactions via social media platforms have made it possible for anyone, irrespective of physical location, to gain access to quick information on events taking place all over the globe. However, the semantic processing of social media data is complicated due to challenges such as language complexity, unstructured data, and ambiguity. In this paper, we proposed the Social Media Analysis Framework for Event Detection (SMAFED). SMAFED aims to facilitate improved semantic analysis of noisy terms in social media streams, improved representation/embedding of social media stream content, and improved summarization of event clusters in social media streams. For this, we employed key concepts such as integrated knowledge base, resolving ambiguity, semantic representation of social media streams, and Semantic Histogram-based Incremental Clustering based on semantic relatedness. Two evaluation experiments were conducted to validate the approach. First, we evaluated the impact of the data enrichment layer of SMAFED. We found that SMAFED outperformed other pre-processing frameworks with a lower loss function of 0.15 on the first dataset and 0.05 on the second dataset. Second, we determined the accuracy of SMAFED at detecting events from social media streams. The result of this second experiment showed that SMAFED outperformed existing event detection approaches with better Precision (0.922), Recall (0.793), and F-Measure (0.853) metric scores. The findings of the study present SMAFED as a more efficient approach to event detection in social media.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://journalofbigdata.springeropen.com/articles/10.1186/s40537-022-00642-y</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\WJZWSKH5\Kolajo et al. - 2022 - Real-time event detection in social media streams through semantic analysis of noisy terms.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-03-31 16:49:59</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><contributors><authors><author>Ren, Jiaqian</author><author>Jiang, Lei</author><author>Peng, Hao</author><author>Cao, Yuwei</author><author>Wu, Jia</author><author>Yu, Philip S.</author><author>He, Lifang</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>From Known to Unknown: Quality-aware Self-improving Graph Neural Network for Open Set Social Event Detection</title><short-title>From Known to Unknown</short-title></titles><keywords><keyword>Computer Science - Social and Information Networks</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2022</year><pub-dates><date>2022-08-15</date></pub-dates></dates><publisher>arXiv</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.48550/arXiv.2208.06973</electronic-resource-num><abstract>State-of-the-art Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) have achieved tremendous success in social event detection tasks when restricted to a closed set of events. However, considering the large amount of data needed for training a neural network and the limited ability of a neural network in handling previously unknown data, it remains a challenge for existing GNN-based methods to operate in an open set setting. To address this problem, we design a Quality-aware Self-improving Graph Neural Network (QSGNN) which extends the knowledge from known to unknown by leveraging the best of known samples and reliable knowledge transfer. Specifically, to fully exploit the labeled data, we propose a novel supervised pairwise loss with an additional orthogonal inter-class relation constraint to train the backbone GNN encoder. The learnt, already-known events further serve as strong reference bases for the unknown ones, which greatly prompts knowledge acquisition and transfer. When the model is generalized to unknown data, to ensure the effectiveness and reliability, we further leverage the reference similarity distribution vectors for pseudo pairwise label generation, selection and quality assessment. Following the diversity principle of active learning, our method selects diverse pair samples with the generated pseudo labels to fine-tune the GNN encoder. Besides, we propose a novel quality-guided optimization in which the contributions of pseudo labels are weighted based on consistency. We thoroughly evaluate our model on two large real-world social event datasets. Experiments demonstrate that our model achieves state-of-the-art results and extends well to unknown events.</abstract><remote-database-name>arXiv.org</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>http://arxiv.org/abs/2208.06973</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\VCW3XHAL\Ren et al. - 2022 - From Known to Unknown Quality-aware Self-improving Graph Neural Network for Open Set Social Event D.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-03-31 16:50:15</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Conference Proceedings">10</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Yue, Zhenrui</author><author>Zeng, Huimin</author><author>Lan, Mengfei</author><author>Ji, Heng</author><author>Wang, Dong</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Zero- and Few-Shot Event Detection via Prompt-Based Meta Learning</title><secondary-title>Proceedings of the 61st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 1: Long Papers)</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Proceedings of the 61st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 1: Long Papers)</full-title></periodical><pages>7928-7943</pages><dates><year>2023</year><pub-dates><date>2023</date></pub-dates></dates><publisher>Association for Computational Linguistics</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.18653/v1/2023.acl-long.440</electronic-resource-num><abstract>With emerging online topics as a source for numerous new events, detecting unseen / rare event types presents an elusive challenge for existing event detection methods, where only limited data access is provided for training. To address the data scarcity problem in event detection, we propose MetaEvent, a meta learningbased framework for zero- and few-shot event detection. Specifically, we sample training tasks from existing event types and perform meta training to search for optimal parameters that quickly adapt to unseen tasks. In our framework, we propose to use the clozebased prompt and a trigger-aware soft verbalizer to efficiently project output to unseen event types. Moreover, we design a contrastive meta objective based on maximum mean discrepancy (MMD) to learn class-separating features. As such, the proposed MetaEvent can perform zero-shot event detection by mapping features to event types without any prior knowledge. In our experiments, we demonstrate the effectiveness of MetaEvent in both zero-shot and few-shot scenarios, where the proposed method achieves state-of-the-art performance in extensive experiments on benchmark datasets FewEvent and MAVEN.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://aclanthology.org/2023.acl-long.440</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\UPG7YTRG\Yue et al. - 2023 - Zero- and Few-Shot Event Detection via Prompt-Based Meta Learning.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-03-31 17:23:43</access-date><custom1>Toronto, Canada</custom1><custom3>Proceedings of the 61st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 1: Long Papers)</custom3></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><contributors><authors><author>Li, Pu</author><author>Yu, Xiaoyan</author><author>Peng, Hao</author><author>Xian, Yantuan</author><author>Wang, Linqin</author><author>Sun, Li</author><author>Zhang, Jingyun</author><author>Yu, Philip S.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Relational Prompt-based Pre-trained Language Models for Social Event Detection</title></titles><keywords><keyword>Computer Science - Computation and Language</keyword><keyword>Computer Science - Social and Information Networks</keyword><keyword>Computer Science - Artificial Intelligence</keyword><keyword>Computer Science - Machine Learning</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2024</year><pub-dates><date>2024-09-10</date></pub-dates></dates><publisher>arXiv</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.48550/arXiv.2404.08263</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Social Event Detection (SED) aims to identify significant events from social streams, and has a wide application ranging from public opinion analysis to risk management. In recent years, Graph Neural Network (GNN) based solutions have achieved state-of-the-art performance. However, GNN-based methods often struggle with missing and noisy edges between messages, affecting the quality of learned message embedding. Moreover, these methods statically initialize node embedding before training, which, in turn, limits the ability to learn from message texts and relations simultaneously. In this paper, we approach social event detection from a new perspective based on Pre-trained Language Models (PLMs), and present RPLM_SED (Relational prompt-based Pre-trained Language Models for Social Event Detection). We first propose a new pairwise message modeling strategy to construct social messages into message pairs with multi-relational sequences. Secondly, a new multi-relational prompt-based pairwise message learning mechanism is proposed to learn more comprehensive message representation from message pairs with multi-relational prompts using PLMs. Thirdly, we design a new clustering constraint to optimize the encoding process by enhancing intra-cluster compactness and inter-cluster dispersion, making the message representation more distinguishable. We evaluate the RPLM_SED on three real-world datasets, demonstrating that the RPLM_SED model achieves state-of-the-art performance in offline, online, low-resource, and long-tail distribution scenarios for social event detection tasks.</abstract><research-notes>Comment: ACM TOIS</research-notes><remote-database-name>arXiv.org</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>http://arxiv.org/abs/2404.08263</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\9VIL3E9N\Li et al. - 2024 - Relational Prompt-based Pre-trained Language Models for Social Event Detection.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-04-01 10:38:40</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Pradhan, Abhaya Kumar</author><author>Mohanty, Hrushikesha</author><author>Lal, Rajendra Prasad</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>EDTBERT: Event Detection and Tracking in Twitter using Graph Clustering and Pre-trained Language Model</title><secondary-title>Procedia Computer Science</secondary-title><short-title>EDTBERT</short-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Procedia Computer Science</full-title><abbr-1>Procedia Computer Science</abbr-1></periodical><pages>481-491</pages><volume>233</volume><dates><year>2024</year><pub-dates><date>2024</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>18770509</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.procs.2024.03.238</electronic-resource-num><abstract>The identification of events from social media platforms such as Twitter (now known as X) is a hot research problem. It has applications in diverse domains such as journalism, marketing, public safety, crisis management and disaster response. The process includes the identification, monitoring, and analysis of events or incidents while they are being discussed or reported on Twitter. When it comes to identifying events from tweets (i.e. feeds from Twitter), many of the currently available event detection methods mainly rely on keyword burstiness features or structural changes in the network. However, due to the intricate characteristics of tweets and the ever-changing nature of events, they frequently fail to recognise noteworthy occurrences before they become trending. Moreover, these methods face difficulties when it comes to capturing the evolving characteristics of events with limited or insufficient contextual information. In this paper, we propose a window-based tweet-processing method called EDTBERT for detecting events and tracking the evolution of events over time. Our proposed method utilizes the structural and semantic affinities that exist among words in tweets. The method starts by generating graph of tweets, where tweets are represented as nodes, and edges are the similarities between tweets. The method utilizes overlapping hashtags and named entities to capture the structural relationship between tweets. Additionally, a pre-trained sentence transformer model, specifically BERT, is employed to collect contextual knowledge and find semantically similar tweets. Next, the graph clustering technique is employed to identify optimized event clusters. Subsequently, our method generates chain of event clusters for each event to track the evolving variation of the event over time by utilising the ”Maximum-Weight Bipartite Graph Matching” (MWBGM) algorithm. The effectiveness of our approach is assessed using standard Tweet Datasets. Our evaluation demonstrates that our approach outperforms the baseline approaches.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S1877050924005970</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\PJMGEEK5\Pradhan et al. - 2024 - EDTBERT Event Detection and Tracking in Twitter using Graph Clustering and Pre-trained Language Mod.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-04-01 11:32:49</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Afyouni, Imad</author><author>Khan, Aamir</author><author>Aghbari, Zaher Al</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Deep-Eware: spatio-temporal social event detection using a hybrid learning model</title><secondary-title>Journal of Big Data</secondary-title><short-title>Deep-Eware</short-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Big Data</full-title><abbr-1>J Big Data</abbr-1></periodical><pages>86</pages><volume>9</volume><number>1</number><issue>1</issue><dates><year>2022</year><pub-dates><date>12/2022</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>2196-1115</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1186/s40537-022-00636-w</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Event detection from social media aims at extracting specific or generic unusual happenings, such as, family reunions, earthquakes, and disease outbreaks, among others. This paper introduces a new perspective for the hybrid extraction and clustering of social events from big social data streams. We rely on a hybrid learning model, where supervised deep learning is used for feature extraction and topic classification, whereas unsupervised spatial clustering is employed to determine the event whereabouts. We present ‘Deep-Eware’, a scalable and efficient event-aware big data platform that integrates data stream and geospatial processing tools for the hybrid extraction and dissemination of spatio-temporal events. We introduce a pure incremental approach for event discovery, by developing unsupervised machine learning and NLP algorithms and by computing events’ lifetime and spatial spanning. The system integrates a semantic keyword generation tool using KeyBERT for dataset preparation. Event classification is performed using CNN and bidirectional LSTM, while hierarchical densitybased spatial clustering was used for location-inference of events. We conduct experiments over Twitter datasets to measure the effectiveness and efficiency of our system. The results demonstrate that this hybrid approach for spatio-temporal event extraction has a major advantage for real-time spatio-temporal event detection and tracking from social media. This leads to the development of unparalleled smart city applications, such as event-enriched trip planning, epidemic disease evolution, and proactive emergency management services.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://journalofbigdata.springeropen.com/articles/10.1186/s40537-022-00636-w</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\VLFUBGCI\Afyouni et al. - 2022 - Deep-Eware spatio-temporal social event detection using a hybrid learning model.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-04-02 11:42:12</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Conference Proceedings">10</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Fedoryszak, Mateusz</author><author>Frederick, Brent</author><author>Rajaram, Vijay</author><author>Zhong, Changtao</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Real-time Event Detection on Social Data Streams</title></titles><periodical><full-title>Proceedings of the 25th ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery &amp; Data Mining</full-title></periodical><pages>2774-2782</pages><keywords><keyword>Computer Science - Social and Information Networks</keyword><keyword>Computer Science - Machine Learning</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2019</year><pub-dates><date>2019-07-25</date></pub-dates></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1145/3292500.3330689</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Social networks are quickly becoming the primary medium for discussing what is happening around real-world events. The information that is generated on social platforms like Twitter can produce rich data streams for immediate insights into ongoing matters and the conversations around them. To tackle the problem of event detection, we model events as a list of clusters of trending entities over time. We describe a real-time system for discovering events that is modular in design and novel in scale and speed: it applies clustering on a large stream with millions of entities per minute and produces a dynamically updated set of events. In order to assess clustering methodologies, we build an evaluation dataset derived from a snapshot of the full Twitter Firehose and propose novel metrics for measuring clustering quality. Through experiments and system profiling, we highlight key results from the offline and online pipelines. Finally, we visualize a high profile event on Twitter to show the importance of modeling the evolution of events, especially those detected from social data streams.</abstract><research-notes>Comment: Accepted as a full paper at KDD 2019 on April 29, 2019</research-notes><remote-database-name>arXiv.org</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.11229</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\R6Y9UV89\Fedoryszak et al. - 2019 - Real-time Event Detection on Social Data Streams.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-04-02 11:42:57</access-date><custom3>Proceedings of the 25th ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery &amp; Data Mining</custom3></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Morabia, Keval</author><author>Murthy, Neti Lalita Bhanu</author><author>Malapati, Aruna</author><author>Samant, Surender</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>SEDTWik: Segmentation-based Event Detection from Tweets Using Wikipedia</title></titles><dates/><abstract>Event Detection has been one of the research areas in Text Mining that has attracted attention during this decade due to the widespread availability of social media data speciﬁcally twitter data. Twitter has become a major source for information about real-world events because of the use of hashtags and the small word limit of Twitter that ensures concise presentation of events. Previous works on event detection from tweets are either applicable to detect localized events or breaking news only or miss out on many important events. This paper presents the problems associated with event detection from tweets and a tweet-segmentation based system for event detection called SEDTWik, an extension to a previous work, that is able to detect newsworthy events occurring at different locations of the world from a wide range of categories. The main idea is to split each tweet and hash-tag into segments, extract bursty segments, cluster them, and summarize them. We evaluated our results on the well-known Events2012 corpus and achieved state-of-the-art results.</abstract><remote-database-name>Zotero</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\ZY5BTXJS\Morabia et al. - SEDTWik Segmentation-based Event Detection from Tweets Using Wikipedia.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Morabia, Keval</author><author>Murthy, Neti Lalita Bhanu</author><author>Malapati, Aruna</author><author>Samant, Surender</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>SEDTWik: Segmentation-based Event Detection from Tweets Using Wikipedia</title></titles><dates/><abstract>Event Detection has been one of the research areas in Text Mining that has attracted attention during this decade due to the widespread availability of social media data speciﬁcally twitter data. Twitter has become a major source for information about real-world events because of the use of hashtags and the small word limit of Twitter that ensures concise presentation of events. Previous works on event detection from tweets are either applicable to detect localized events or breaking news only or miss out on many important events. This paper presents the problems associated with event detection from tweets and a tweet-segmentation based system for event detection called SEDTWik, an extension to a previous work, that is able to detect newsworthy events occurring at different locations of the world from a wide range of categories. The main idea is to split each tweet and hash-tag into segments, extract bursty segments, cluster them, and summarize them. We evaluated our results on the well-known Events2012 corpus and achieved state-of-the-art results.</abstract><remote-database-name>Zotero</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\STIV4F46\Morabia et al. - SEDTWik Segmentation-based Event Detection from Tweets Using Wikipedia.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Conference Proceedings">10</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Marwen, Bouabid</author><author>Mohamed, Farah</author><author>Riadh, Farah Imed</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Suspicious Local Event Detection in Social Media and Remote Sensing: Towards a Geosocial Dataset Construction</title><secondary-title>2020 5th International Conference on Advanced Technologies for Signal and Image Processing (ATSIP)</secondary-title><short-title>Suspicious Local Event Detection in Social Media and Remote Sensing</short-title></titles><periodical><full-title>2020 5th International Conference on Advanced Technologies for Signal and Image Processing (ATSIP)</full-title></periodical><pages>1-6</pages><dates><year>2020</year><pub-dates><date>9/2020</date></pub-dates></dates><publisher>IEEE</publisher><isbn>978-1-7281-7513-3</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1109/ATSIP49331.2020.9231798</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Remote sensing is a powerful technology for earth observation. However, the spatial, spectral, and temporal resolution of the imagery are imposing various limits. Lately, with the rise of the internet and smart mobile devices, social media with location-based information has been rapidly emerging. These circumstances led to the prevailing of new scenarios where ﬁnegrained details of social bookmarking websites are enhanced with the wide coverage of satellites. Social media and satellites are both valuable sources of data. An event-driven data, designating either normal common events or unusual suspicious ones that may threaten human lives or damage the infrastructure. In this paper, we provide an insight into the present state of knowledge to better address the task of local suspicious event detection and linking social media with satellite imagery. Also, to track suspicious local events, we treated the detection problem as a retrospective problem by training different classiﬁers on the crisisLexT26 dataset. Furthermore, we introduced how to use the available geo-locations in the dataset to construct a geo-social dataset by linking it with remote sensing and retrieving satellite imagery before and after the event occurrence.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9231798/</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\Q6R56JSY\Marwen et al. - 2020 - Suspicious Local Event Detection in Social Media and Remote Sensing Towards a Geosocial Dataset Con.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-04-02 11:44:18</access-date><custom1>Sousse, Tunisia</custom1><custom3>2020 5th International Conference on Advanced Technologies for Signal and Image Processing (ATSIP)</custom3></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Conference Proceedings">10</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Marwen, Bouabid</author><author>Mohamed, Farah</author><author>Riadh, Farah Imed</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Suspicious Local Event Detection in Social Media and Remote Sensing: Towards a Geosocial Dataset Construction</title><secondary-title>2020 5th International Conference on Advanced Technologies for Signal and Image Processing (ATSIP)</secondary-title><short-title>Suspicious Local Event Detection in Social Media and Remote Sensing</short-title></titles><periodical><full-title>2020 5th International Conference on Advanced Technologies for Signal and Image Processing (ATSIP)</full-title></periodical><pages>1-6</pages><dates><year>2020</year><pub-dates><date>9/2020</date></pub-dates></dates><publisher>IEEE</publisher><isbn>978-1-7281-7513-3</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1109/ATSIP49331.2020.9231798</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Remote sensing is a powerful technology for earth observation. However, the spatial, spectral, and temporal resolution of the imagery are imposing various limits. Lately, with the rise of the internet and smart mobile devices, social media with location-based information has been rapidly emerging. These circumstances led to the prevailing of new scenarios where ﬁnegrained details of social bookmarking websites are enhanced with the wide coverage of satellites. Social media and satellites are both valuable sources of data. An event-driven data, designating either normal common events or unusual suspicious ones that may threaten human lives or damage the infrastructure. In this paper, we provide an insight into the present state of knowledge to better address the task of local suspicious event detection and linking social media with satellite imagery. Also, to track suspicious local events, we treated the detection problem as a retrospective problem by training different classiﬁers on the crisisLexT26 dataset. Furthermore, we introduced how to use the available geo-locations in the dataset to construct a geo-social dataset by linking it with remote sensing and retrieving satellite imagery before and after the event occurrence.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9231798/</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\8DLZJAT5\Marwen et al. - 2020 - Suspicious Local Event Detection in Social Media and Remote Sensing Towards a Geosocial Dataset Con.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-04-02 11:44:27</access-date><custom1>Sousse, Tunisia</custom1><custom3>2020 5th International Conference on Advanced Technologies for Signal and Image Processing (ATSIP)</custom3></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><contributors><authors><author>Zhang, Yihong</author><author>Shirakawa, Masumi</author><author>Hara, Takahiro</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>A General Method for Event Detection on Social Media</title></titles><keywords><keyword>Computer Science - Information Retrieval</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2021</year><pub-dates><date>2021-06-04</date></pub-dates></dates><publisher>arXiv</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.48550/arXiv.2106.02250</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Event detection on social media has attracted a number of researches, given the recent availability of large volumes of social media discussions. Previous works on social media event detection either assume a speciﬁc type of event, or assume certain behavior of observed variables. In this paper, we propose a general method for event detection on social media that makes few assumptions. The main assumption we make is that when an event occurs, aﬀected semantic aspects will behave diﬀerently from its usual behavior. We generalize the representation of time units based on word embeddings of social media text, and propose an algorithm to detect events in time series in a general sense. In the experimental evaluation, we use a novel setting to test if our method and baseline methods can exhaustively catch all real-world news in the test period. The evaluation results show that when the event is quite unusual with regard to the base social media discussion, it can be captured more eﬀectively with our method. Our method can be easily implemented and can be treated as a starting point for more speciﬁc applications.</abstract><research-notes>Comment: Accepted for presentation in the 25th European Conference on Advances in Databases and Information Systems (ADBIS 2021)</research-notes><remote-database-name>arXiv.org</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>http://arxiv.org/abs/2106.02250</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\45FPF36D\Zhang et al. - 2021 - A General Method for Event Detection on Social Media.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-04-02 11:44:37</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><contributors><authors><author>Zhang, Yihong</author><author>Shirakawa, Masumi</author><author>Hara, Takahiro</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>A General Method for Event Detection on Social Media</title></titles><keywords><keyword>Computer Science - Information Retrieval</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2021</year><pub-dates><date>2021-06-04</date></pub-dates></dates><publisher>arXiv</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.48550/arXiv.2106.02250</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Event detection on social media has attracted a number of researches, given the recent availability of large volumes of social media discussions. Previous works on social media event detection either assume a speciﬁc type of event, or assume certain behavior of observed variables. In this paper, we propose a general method for event detection on social media that makes few assumptions. The main assumption we make is that when an event occurs, aﬀected semantic aspects will behave diﬀerently from its usual behavior. We generalize the representation of time units based on word embeddings of social media text, and propose an algorithm to detect events in time series in a general sense. In the experimental evaluation, we use a novel setting to test if our method and baseline methods can exhaustively catch all real-world news in the test period. The evaluation results show that when the event is quite unusual with regard to the base social media discussion, it can be captured more eﬀectively with our method. Our method can be easily implemented and can be treated as a starting point for more speciﬁc applications.</abstract><research-notes>Comment: Accepted for presentation in the 25th European Conference on Advances in Databases and Information Systems (ADBIS 2021)</research-notes><remote-database-name>arXiv.org</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>http://arxiv.org/abs/2106.02250</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\SYNHCMVK\Zhang et al. - 2021 - A General Method for Event Detection on Social Media.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-04-02 11:44:41</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Ghaemi, Zeinab</author><author>Farnaghi, Mahdi</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Event detection from geotagged tweets considering spatial autocorrelation and heterogeneity</title><secondary-title>Journal of Spatial Science</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Spatial Science</full-title><abbr-1>Journal of Spatial Science</abbr-1></periodical><pages>353-371</pages><volume>68</volume><number>3</number><issue>3</issue><dates><year>2023</year><pub-dates><date>2023-07-03</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>1449-8596, 1836-5655</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1080/14498596.2021.2002201</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Twitter, as the most popular social media platform, has made a great revolution in producing real-time user-generated data. This research aims to propose a method to extract the latent spatial pattern from geotagged tweets. We take both spatial autocorrelation and spatial heterogeneity into account while revealing the underlying pattern from geotagged tweets. Moreover, the textual similarity is considered to extract spatial-textual clusters. The method was implemented and tested during hurricane Dorian on the east coast of the U.S. The results proved the superiority of the proposed method against Moran’s Index and VDBSCAN algorithms in extracting clusters with various densities.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/14498596.2021.2002201</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\XHV2K86I\Ghaemi and Farnaghi - 2023 - Event detection from geotagged tweets considering spatial autocorrelation and heterogeneity.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-04-02 11:44:51</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Ghaemi, Zeinab</author><author>Farnaghi, Mahdi</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Event detection from geotagged tweets considering spatial autocorrelation and heterogeneity</title><secondary-title>Journal of Spatial Science</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Spatial Science</full-title><abbr-1>Journal of Spatial Science</abbr-1></periodical><pages>353-371</pages><volume>68</volume><number>3</number><issue>3</issue><dates><year>2023</year><pub-dates><date>2023-07-03</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>1449-8596, 1836-5655</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1080/14498596.2021.2002201</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Twitter, as the most popular social media platform, has made a great revolution in producing real-time user-generated data. This research aims to propose a method to extract the latent spatial pattern from geotagged tweets. We take both spatial autocorrelation and spatial heterogeneity into account while revealing the underlying pattern from geotagged tweets. Moreover, the textual similarity is considered to extract spatial-textual clusters. The method was implemented and tested during hurricane Dorian on the east coast of the U.S. The results proved the superiority of the proposed method against Moran’s Index and VDBSCAN algorithms in extracting clusters with various densities.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/14498596.2021.2002201</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\FRAG7QMU\Ghaemi and Farnaghi - 2023 - Event detection from geotagged tweets considering spatial autocorrelation and heterogeneity.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-04-02 11:44:54</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><contributors><authors><author>Yu, Xiaoyan</author><author>Wei, Yifan</author><author>Zhou, Shuaishuai</author><author>Yang, Zhiwei</author><author>Sun, Li</author><author>Peng, Hao</author><author>Zhu, Liehuang</author><author>Yu, Philip S.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Towards Effective, Efficient and Unsupervised Social Event Detection in the Hyperbolic Space</title></titles><keywords><keyword>Computer Science - Computation and Language</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2024</year><pub-dates><date>2024-12-14</date></pub-dates></dates><publisher>arXiv</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.48550/arXiv.2412.10712</electronic-resource-num><abstract>The vast, complex, and dynamic nature of social message data has posed challenges to social event detection (SED). Despite considerable effort, these challenges persist, often resulting in inadequately expressive message representations (ineffective) and prolonged learning durations (inefficient). In response to the challenges, this work introduces an unsupervised framework, HyperSED (Hyperbolic SED). Specifically, the proposed framework first models social messages into semantic-based message anchors, and then leverages the structure of the anchor graph and the expressiveness of the hyperbolic space to acquire structure- and geometry-aware anchor representations. Finally, HyperSED builds the partitioning tree of the anchor message graph by incorporating differentiable structural information as the reflection of the detected events. Extensive experiments on public datasets demonstrate HyperSED’s competitive performance, along with a substantial improvement in efficiency compared to the current state-of-the-art unsupervised paradigm. Statistically, HyperSED boosts incremental SED by an average of 2%, 2%, and 25% in NMI, AMI, and ARI, respectively; enhancing efficiency by up to 37.41 times and at least 12.10 times, illustrating the advancement of the proposed framework. Our code is publicly available at https://github.com/ XiaoyanWork/HyperSED.</abstract><research-notes>Comment: Accepted to AAAI 2025</research-notes><remote-database-name>arXiv.org</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>http://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10712</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\ABDTR5IJ\Yu et al. - 2024 - Towards Effective, Efficient and Unsupervised Social Event Detection in the Hyperbolic Space.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-04-02 17:16:53</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Conference Proceedings">10</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Cao, Yuwei</author><author>Peng, Hao</author><author>Wu, Jia</author><author>Dou, Yingtong</author><author>Li, Jianxin</author><author>Yu, Philip S.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Knowledge-Preserving Incremental Social Event Detection via Heterogeneous GNNs</title></titles><periodical><full-title>Proceedings of the Web Conference 2021</full-title></periodical><pages>3383-3395</pages><keywords><keyword>Computer Science - Machine Learning</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2021</year><pub-dates><date>2021-04-19</date></pub-dates></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1145/3442381.3449834</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Social events provide valuable insights into group social behaviors and public concerns and therefore have many applications in fields such as product recommendation and crisis management. The complexity and streaming nature of social messages make it appealing to address social event detection in an incremental learning setting, where acquiring, preserving, and extending knowledge are major concerns. Most existing methods, including those based on incremental clustering and community detection, learn limited amounts of knowledge as they ignore the rich semantics and structural information contained in social data. Moreover, they cannot memorize previously acquired knowledge. In this paper, we propose a novel Knowledge-Preserving Incremental Heterogeneous Graph Neural Network (KPGNN) for incremental social event detection. To acquire more knowledge, KPGNN models complex social messages into unified social graphs to facilitate data utilization and explores the expressive power of GNNs for knowledge extraction. To continuously adapt to the incoming data, KPGNN adopts contrastive loss terms that cope with a changing number of event classes. It also leverages the inductive learning ability of GNNs to efficiently detect events and extends its knowledge from previously unseen data. To deal with large social streams, KPGNN adopts a mini-batch subgraph sampling strategy for scalable training, and periodically removes obsolete data to maintain a dynamic embedding space. KPGNN requires no feature engineering and has few hyperparameters to tune. Extensive experiment results demonstrate the superiority of KPGNN over various baselines.</abstract><research-notes>Comment: This work has been accepted to The Web Conference 2021</research-notes><remote-database-name>arXiv.org</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>http://arxiv.org/abs/2101.08747</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\LDVKBEZB\Cao et al. - 2021 - Knowledge-Preserving Incremental Social Event Detection via Heterogeneous GNNs.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-04-02 17:20:28</access-date><custom3>Proceedings of the Web Conference 2021</custom3></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Conference Proceedings">10</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Qiu, Zitai</author><author>Ma, Congbo</author><author>Wu, Jia</author><author>Yang, Jian</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>An Efficient Automatic Meta-Path Selection for Social Event Detection via Hyperbolic Space</title><secondary-title>WWW '24: The ACM Web Conference 2024</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Proceedings of the ACM Web Conference 2024</full-title></periodical><pages>2519-2529</pages><dates><year>2024</year><pub-dates><date>2024-05-13</date></pub-dates></dates><publisher>ACM</publisher><isbn>979-8-4007-0171-9</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1145/3589334.3645526</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Social events reflect changes in communities, such as natural disasters and emergencies. Detection of these situations can help residents and organizations in the community avoid danger and reduce losses. The complex nature of social messages makes social event detection on social media challenging. The challenges that have a greater impact on social media detection models are as follows: (1) the amount of social media data is huge but its availability is small; (2) social media data is a tree structure and traditional Euclidean space embedding will distort embedded features; and (3) the heterogeneity of social media networks makes existing models unable to capture rich information well. To solve the above challenges, we propose a Heterogeneous Information Graph representation via Hyperbolic space combined with an Automatic Meta-path selection (GraphHAM) model, an efficient framework that automatically selects the meta-path’s weight and combines hyperbolic space to learn information on social media. In particular, we apply an efficient automatic meta-path selection technique and convert the selected meta-path into a vector, thereby reducing the requisite amount of labeled data for the model. We also design a novel Hyperbolic Multi-Layer Perceptron (HMLP) to further learn the semantic and structural information of social information. Extensive experiments show that GraphHAM can achieve outstanding performance on real-world data using only 20% of the whole dataset as the training set. Our code can be found on GitHub 1.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3589334.3645526</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\2VYE3MJE\Qiu et al. - 2024 - An Efficient Automatic Meta-Path Selection for Social Event Detection via Hyperbolic Space.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-04-02 20:30:35</access-date><custom1>Singapore Singapore</custom1><custom3>Proceedings of the ACM Web Conference 2024</custom3></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Conference Proceedings">10</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Yang, Zhiwei</author><author>Wei, Yuecen</author><author>Li, Haoran</author><author>Li, Qian</author><author>Jiang, Lei</author><author>Sun, Li</author><author>Yu, Xiaoyan</author><author>Hu, Chunming</author><author>Peng, Hao</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Adaptive Differentially Private Structural Entropy Minimization for Unsupervised Social Event Detection</title></titles><periodical><full-title>Proceedings of the 33rd ACM International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management</full-title></periodical><pages>2950-2960</pages><keywords><keyword>Computer Science - Social and Information Networks</keyword><keyword>Computer Science - Artificial Intelligence</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2024</year><pub-dates><date>2024-10-21</date></pub-dates></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1145/3627673.3679537</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Social event detection refers to extracting relevant message clusters from social media data streams to represent specific events in the real world. Social event detection is important in numerous areas, such as opinion analysis, social safety, and decision-making. Most current methods are supervised and require access to large amounts of data. These methods need prior knowledge of the events and carry a high risk of leaking sensitive information in the messages, making them less applicable in open-world settings. Therefore, conducting unsupervised detection while fully utilizing the rich information in the messages and protecting data privacy remains a significant challenge. To this end, we propose a novel social event detection framework, ADP-SEMEvent, an unsupervised social event detection method that prioritizes privacy. Specifically, ADP-SEMEvent is divided into two stages, i.e., the construction stage of the private message graph and the clustering stage of the private message graph. In the first stage, an adaptive differential privacy approach is used to construct a private message graph. In this process, our method can adaptively apply differential privacy based on the events occurring each day in an open environment to maximize the use of the privacy budget. In the second stage, to address the reduction in data utility caused by noise, a novel 2-dimensional structural entropy minimization algorithm based on optimal subgraphs is used to detect events in the message graph.</abstract><research-notes>Comment: Accepted to ACM CIKM 2024</research-notes><remote-database-name>arXiv.org</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18274</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\2NCXV4PD\Yang et al. - 2024 - Adaptive Differentially Private Structural Entropy Minimization for Unsupervised Social Event Detect.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-04-02 20:42:16</access-date><custom3>Proceedings of the 33rd ACM International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management</custom3></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><contributors><authors><author>Cao, Yuwei</author><author>Peng, Hao</author><author>Yu, Zhengtao</author><author>Yu, Philip S.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Hierarchical and Incremental Structural Entropy Minimization for Unsupervised Social Event Detection</title></titles><keywords><keyword>Computer Science - Social and Information Networks</keyword><keyword>Computer Science - Machine Learning</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2023</year><pub-dates><date>2023-12-19</date></pub-dates></dates><publisher>arXiv</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.48550/arXiv.2312.11891</electronic-resource-num><abstract>As a trending approach for social event detection, graph neural network (GNN)-based methods enable a fusion of natural language semantics and the complex social network structural information, thus showing SOTA performance. However, GNN-based methods can miss useful message correlations. Moreover, they require manual labeling for training and predetermining the number of events for prediction. In this work, we address social event detection via graph structural entropy (SE) minimization. While keeping the merits of the GNN-based methods, the proposed framework, HISEvent, constructs more informative message graphs, is unsupervised, and does not require the number of events given a priori. Specifically, we incrementally explore the graph neighborhoods using 1-dimensional (1D) SE minimization to supplement the existing message graph with edges between semantically related messages. We then detect events from the message graph by hierarchically minimizing 2-dimensional (2D) SE. Our proposed 1D and 2D SE minimization algorithms are customized for social event detection and effectively tackle the efficiency problem of the existing SE minimization algorithms. Extensive experiments show that HISEvent consistently outperforms GNN-based methods and achieves the new SOTA for social event detection under both closed- and open-set settings while being efficient and robust.</abstract><research-notes>Comment: Accepted to AAAI 2024</research-notes><remote-database-name>arXiv.org</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.11891</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\DMFCCWIQ\Cao et al. - 2023 - Hierarchical and Incremental Structural Entropy Minimization for Unsupervised Social Event Detection.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-04-03 10:27:22</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><contributors><authors><author>Ren, Jiaqian</author><author>Peng, Hao</author><author>Jiang, Lei</author><author>Liu, Zhiwei</author><author>Wu, Jia</author><author>Yu, Zhengtao</author><author>Yu, Philip S.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Uncertainty-guided Boundary Learning for Imbalanced Social Event Detection</title></titles><keywords><keyword>Computer Science - Artificial Intelligence</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2023</year><pub-dates><date>2023-10-30</date></pub-dates></dates><publisher>arXiv</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.48550/arXiv.2310.19247</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Real-world social events typically exhibit a severe class-imbalance distribution, which makes the trained detection model encounter a serious generalization challenge. Most studies solve this problem from the frequency perspective and emphasize the representation or classifier learning for tail classes. While in our observation, compared to the rarity of classes, the calibrated uncertainty estimated from well-trained evidential deep learning networks better reflects model performance. To this end, we propose a novel uncertainty-guided class imbalance learning framework - UCLSED, and its variant - UCL-ECSED, for imbalanced social event detection tasks. We aim to improve the overall model performance by enhancing model generalization to those uncertain classes. Considering performance degradation usually comes from misclassifying samples as their confusing neighboring classes, we focus on boundary learning in latent space and classifier learning with high-quality uncertainty estimation. First, we design a novel uncertainty-guided contrastive learning loss, namely UCL and its variant - UCL-EC, to manipulate distinguishable representation distribution for imbalanced data. During training, they force all classes, especially uncertain ones, to adaptively adjust a clear separable boundary in the feature space. Second, to obtain more robust and accurate class uncertainty, we combine the results of multi-view evidential classifiers via the Dempster-Shafer theory under the supervision of an additional calibration method. We conduct experiments on three severely imbalanced social event datasets including Events2012 100, Events2018 100, and CrisisLexT 7. Our model significantly improves social event representation and classification tasks in almost all classes, especially those uncertain ones.</abstract><research-notes>Comment: Accepted by TKDE 2023</research-notes><remote-database-name>arXiv.org</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>http://arxiv.org/abs/2310.19247</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\ZZUFUWV3\Ren et al. - 2023 - Uncertainty-guided Boundary Learning for Imbalanced Social Event Detection.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-04-03 12:58:57</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Journal Article">17</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Guo, Yuanyuan</author><author>Zang, Zehua</author><author>Gao, Hang</author><author>Xu, Xiao</author><author>Wang, Rui</author><author>Liu, Lixiang</author><author>Li, Jiangmeng</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Unsupervised Social Event Detection via Hybrid Graph Contrastive Learning and Reinforced Incremental Clustering</title><secondary-title>Knowledge-Based Systems</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Knowledge-Based Systems</full-title><abbr-1>Knowledge-Based Systems</abbr-1></periodical><pages>111225</pages><volume>284</volume><keywords><keyword>Computer Science - Social and Information Networks</keyword><keyword>Computer Science - Artificial Intelligence</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2024</year><pub-dates><date>01/2024</date></pub-dates></dates><isbn>09507051</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.knosys.2023.111225</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Detecting events from social media data streams is gradually attracting researchers. The innate challenge for detecting events is to extract discriminative information from social media data thereby assigning the data into different events. Due to the excessive diversity and high updating frequency of social data, using supervised approaches to detect events from social messages is hardly achieved. To this end, recent works explore learning discriminative information from social messages by leveraging graph contrastive learning (GCL) and embedding clustering in an unsupervised manner. However, two intrinsic issues exist in benchmark methods: conventional GCL can only roughly explore partial attributes, thereby insufficiently learning the discriminative information of social messages; for benchmark methods, the learned embeddings are clustered in the latent space by taking advantage of certain specific prior knowledge, which conflicts with the principle of unsupervised learning paradigm. In this paper, we propose a novel unsupervised social media event detection method via hybrid graph contrastive learning and reinforced incremental clustering (HCRC), which uses hybrid graph contrastive learning to comprehensively learn semantic and structural discriminative information from social messages and reinforced incremental clustering to perform efficient clustering in a solidly unsupervised manner. We conduct comprehensive experiments to evaluate HCRC on the Twitter and Maven datasets. The experimental results demonstrate that our approach yields consistent significant performance boosts. In traditional incremental setting, semi-supervised incremental setting and solidly unsupervised setting, the model performance has achieved maximum improvements of 53%, 45%, and 37%, respectively.</abstract><research-notes>Comment: Accepted by Knowledge-Based Systems</research-notes><remote-database-name>arXiv.org</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>http://arxiv.org/abs/2312.08374</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\NJFVFVCK\Guo et al. - 2024 - Unsupervised Social Event Detection via Hybrid Graph Contrastive Learning and Reinforced Incremental.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-04-03 13:44:36</access-date></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><ref-type name="Conference Proceedings">10</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Li, Quanzhi</author><author>Chao, Yang</author><author>Li, Dong</author><author>Lu, Yao</author><author>Zhang, Chi</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Event Detection from Social Media Stream: Methods, Datasets and Opportunities</title><secondary-title>2022 IEEE International Conference on Big Data (Big Data)</secondary-title><short-title>Event Detection from Social Media Stream</short-title></titles><periodical><full-title>2022 IEEE International Conference on Big Data (Big Data)</full-title></periodical><pages>3509-3516</pages><dates><year>2022</year><pub-dates><date>2022-12-17</date></pub-dates></dates><publisher>IEEE</publisher><isbn>978-1-6654-8045-1</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1109/BigData55660.2022.10020411</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Social media streams contain large and diverse amount of information, ranging from daily-life stories to the latest global and local events and news. Twitter, especially, allows a fast spread of events happening real time, and enables individuals and organizations to stay informed of the events happening now. Event detection from social media data poses different challenges from traditional text and is a research area that has attracted much attention in recent years. In this paper, we survey a wide range of event detection methods for Twitter data stream, helping readers understand the recent development in this area. We present the datasets available to the public. Furthermore, a few research opportunities are discussed as potential future research directions.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/10020411/</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\ZZ7QEC3I\Li et al. - 2022 - Event Detection from Social Media Stream Methods, Datasets and Opportunities.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-04-06 10:08:55</access-date><custom1>Osaka, Japan</custom1><custom3>2022 IEEE International Conference on Big Data (Big Data)</custom3></record><record><database name="MyLibrary">MyLibrary</database><source-app name="Zotero">Zotero</source-app><contributors><authors><author>Abagissa, Asres Temam</author><author>Saxena, Shruti</author><author>Chandra, Joydeep</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Distilbert-gnn: a Powerful Approach to Social Media Event Detection</title><short-title>Distilbert-gnn</short-title></titles><dates><year>2024</year><pub-dates><date>2024-04-04</date></pub-dates></dates><publisher>In Review</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.21203/rs.3.rs-4193412/v1</electronic-resource-num><abstract>Finding events actively discussed locally or globally is a signiﬁcant problem when mining social media data streams. Identifying such events can serve as an early warning system in an event such as an accident, a protest, an election, or other breaking news. However, with the massive volume of social media feeds streaming, early detection of such events is inherently complex. Despite the advances in social media event detection, existing methods often struggle with the dynamic nature of social media, the volume and velocity of data, and the ambiguity in usergenerated content. On the contrary, several relational aspects are present in social media that, if suitably handled and exploited, can improve detection performance. To mitigate these challenges, we propose ”DistilBERT-GNN,” an incremental event detection framework that leverages DistilBERT and Graph Neural Networks (GNNs). By integrating DistilBERT’s real-time contextual understanding with GNNs’ ability to capture evolving relationships in social media networks, our framework aims to detect and track events as they emerge and evolve. We assess the eﬀectiveness of our approach through comparative analysis against various state-of-the-art event detection methods on a real-world Twitter dataset. Our experimental result demonstrates that DistilBERT-GNN outperforms the baselines with NMI, AMI, and ARI metrics by 0.72, 0.53, and 0.24, respectively.</abstract><remote-database-name>DOI.org (Crossref)</remote-database-name><language>en</language><urls><web-urls><url>https://www.researchsquare.com/article/rs-4193412/v1</url></web-urls><pdf-urls><url>C:\Users\Hasan\Zotero\storage\8UCWVYQQ\Abagissa et al. - 2024 - Distilbert-gnn a Powerful Approach to Social Media Event Detection.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><access-date>2025-04-06 18:10:30</access-date></record></records></xml>